Guide to the Royal Cortissoz Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Royal Cortissoz papers
1864-1955
1920-1955
YCAL MSS 146
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.76
(16 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, a small quantity of personal papers, and printed material relating to the life and career of Royal Cortissoz. Correspondents include Henry Bacon, Bernard Berenson, Joseph Duveen, John La Farge, Clarence Mackay, Whitelaw Reid, Edmund Clarence Stedman, William Winter, and other critics and friends. The personal papers include drafts of articles and lectures by Cortissoz and awards presented to him. Printed material includes copies of writings by Cortissoz, articles concerning him, and miscellaneous programs and invitations. Also included are notes, memoranda and a sketchbook by John La Farge, collected by Cortissoz in the course of research.
Cortissoz, Royal, 1869-1948
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Primarily gift of the Executor and heirs of Royal Cortissoz, 1953. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile in boxes 15-16 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies or photographic prints for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
ROYAL CORTISSOZ, 1869-1948
Royal Cortissoz was born in Brooklyn, New York, the son of Francisco Emmanuel Cortissoz and Julia da Costo Cortissoz. In 1883 he went to work for the architectural firm of McKim, Mead & White. In 1889 he was appointed art critic for The Commercial Advertiser, and on October 1, 1891 he was named art critic for the New York Tribune (later the New York Herald-Tribune ), a position he held for more than fifty years. Cortissoz was a champion of traditional and representational art, and considered modernist art "sterile." He was the author of many critical articles, three biographies, and six volumes of essays, and became a nationally-known and highly popular lecturer on the arts, particularly painting. Cortissoz also wrote inscriptions for many memorials, the most famous of which appears behind the statue of Lincoln in the Lincoln Memorial.
In 1897 he married Ellen Mackay Hutchinson, co-editor with Edmund Clarence Stedman of The Library of American Literature and an author herself. His fiftieth anniversary with the Herald-Tribune was celebrated by many colleagues and admirers. Royal Cortissoz died in New York City on October 17, 1948. At the time of his death, Henry McBride noted his dislike of modern art, but added: "These innovators could not have asked for a fairer opponent. They will miss him. He created the argument and when there is no argument a movement lies flat."
Scope and Contents
The Royal Cortissoz Papers consist of correspondence and a small quantity of personal papers and printed materials which document aspects of the professional life of the art critic and lecturer Royal Cortissoz. The collection has been organized into two series. Series I, Cortissoz Correspondence and Manuscripts, and Series II. Printed Material. The papers span the dates 1864-1959, with the bulk of the material dating from between 1920 and 1955.
Series I, Cortissoz Correspondence and Manuscripts, is housed in boxes 1-12. The material is arranged alphabetically by author, with "Letter General" files for each letter preceding files devoted to individual correspondents. Letters by Cortissoz himself, as well as drafts of articles, research notes, and other personal material, are found listed alphabetically by type of material and then by subject or addressee under the entry for Cortissoz.
Major correspondents include the sculptor Henry Bacon; art critic Bernard Berenson; muralist Edwin Blashfield; art dealer Joseph Duveen; art collector Clarence Mackay; editor and author Edmund Clarence Stedman; drama critic William Winter; Whitelaw Reid; and the author Katharine Prescott Wormeley. Typical subjects include the state of contemporary art; opinions of various painters and their works; discussion of articles and books in progress; professional societies and meetings; personal and family news, and plans for social engagements and travel.
Material concerning the artist John La Farge is located in Box 7, folders 281-291, and includes four folders of letters from LaFarge to Cortissoz, many expressing his appreciation for favorable comments and reviews; four folders of notes and memoranda on La Farge used by Cortissoz in preparing his biography; and a small sketchbook of La Farge's containing pencil sketches of figures and notes for larger works.
Folders 85-110 contain notes for and drafts of various addresses and pieces planned by Cortissoz, including several on American art and artists; folders 110-163 contain letters by Cortissoz. These include some retained carbons, but are mostly originals or photostats added to the papers by Davenport West, Cortissoz's executor, who solicited them from their recipients for inclusion in the collection. It should also be noted that many of the individual files in this series contain correspondence from West, particularly self-addressed reply postcards, requesting participation in this project. These requests were not uniformly successful: Ogden Reid, for example, responded that "The letters that I have from 'Uncle Bob' are of a personal nature and therefore in my opinion not suitable for the Yale University collection" (Box 9, folder 364).
Series II, Printed Material, is arranged in five subseries. The first three contain printed copies of works by Cortissoz: Addresses by Cortissoz; Articles by Cortissoz; and Book Reviews by Cortissoz. Contents include the text of his speech at the dedication of the Henry Bacon Memorial, articles on landscape art, Japanese painting, and Whistler; and reviews of several biographies.
The remaining two subseries, Articles about Cortissoz and Other Printed Material, contain biographical articles, including fiftieth anniversary tributes; memorial tributes to friends of Cortissoz; and programs, including the program for the dedication of the Lincoln Memorial in 1922 and a program for a musical evening signed by Rachmaninoff, Kreisler, Stravinsky, and Damrosch, among others.
Oversize material is housed in Box 14.
Art criticism -- United States; Art, American -- 20th Century; Sketchbooks; Art critics -- United States; Bacon, Henry, 1866-1924; Berenson, Bernard, 1865-1959; Blashfield, Edwin Howland, 1848-1936; Cortissoz, Royal, 1869-1948; Dewing, Thomas Wilmer, 1851-1938; Duveen, Joseph Duveen, Baron, 1869-1939; La Farge, John, 1835-1910; Mackay, Clarence H. (Clarence Hungerford), 1874-1938; Platt, Charles A. (Charles Adams), 1861-1933; Reid, Whitelaw, 1837-1912; Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1833-1908; Winter, William, 1836-1917; Wormeley, Katharine Prescott; Zigrosser, Carl, 1891-1975
- Cortissoz Correspondence and Manuscripts, 1864-1959; Series I; 5.04; (12 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The series is arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Bibliographical file, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified, 1907-38 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - "A" general, 1910-54, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    Adams, Edward Dean
    Aldrich, M. Charles
    Aldrich, Donald B.
    Alexander, Harriet C.
    Amateis, Edmond R.
    American Academy of Arts and Letters
    American Academy in Rome
    Ames, Winthrop
    Andrews, A.G.
    Angell, James R.
    Architectural Forum
    Architectural League of New York
    Armstrong, Hamilton Fish
    Aronson, N.
    At----, Riozo
  - Abbey, Edward, Mr. and Mrs., 1927-29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Adams, Henry, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Adams, Herbert Adams, Adeline, 1914-45 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Agnew, Colin and Cornelius, 1927-32 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Aitken, Charles, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Aldrich, Chester and Amey, 1930-40, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Aldrich, Richard, 1953-54, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Aman, Jean, 1913, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - American Art Association, 1919, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - American Institute of Architects, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Anthony, Susan B. [to Mrs. Hutchinson], 1904 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Arms, John Taylor, 1939-45 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Atherton, Gertrude, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Avery, Samuel Putnam, 1919, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "B" general, 1907-53, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21-25)
    Babcock, E.C.
    Bach, Richard F.
    Bache, Jules S.
    Bailey, Wesley L.
    Bacon, Francis H.
    Barker, Virgil
    Barnum, Dana D.
    Barry, Adrienne
    Bartlett, Frederic
    Baum, Dwight James
    Baur, W.C.
    Bax, Emily
    Beckman, W.B.
    Belmont, Perry
    Belmont, Eleanor
    Benedict, H.H.
    Benjamin, -----
    Bennett, James O'Donnell
    Bennett Jr., John J.
    Berry, Watson B.
    Bigelow, Grace
    Bigelow, John
    Bigelow, Poultney
    Bimbauer, Martin
    Bishop, C.W.
    Bizon, ----
    Biven, Oswald
    Blake, Irving
    Blaney, Dwight
    Bliss, Bill
    Bliss, C.N.
    Bliss, Lilian
    Bliss, Laurence T., Mrs.
    Bliss, M.M.
    Bliven, Bruce
    Bluedret, Harriet Dawson
    Bogert, Marston Taylor
    Boardman, H.S.
    Boldini, G.
    Boody, Edgar
    Bouchor, I.F.
    Bowdoin College
    Bowski, Adolf
    Boylav, William
    Bragança, Anita de
    Breck, Edward
    Breck, Teddy
    Breckenridge, Mr.
    Bridges, Robert
    Bridgman, A.
    Browne, George Elmer
    Bruce, Augustus
    Bruce, H. Addington
    Bruce, Lauretta A.
    Brush, George de Forest
    Br--, Elizabeth
    Buell, Clarence C.
    Bullen, Henry L.
    Burgoyne, St. George
    Burlingame, E.L.
    Burroughs, Alan
    Butler, Charles
  - Bacon, Henry: Address, 1926, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Bacon, Henry Bacon, Laura, 1912-22 (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
  - Ballin, Hugo, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Barrie, Erwin S., 1928-41 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Beaux, Cecilia, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Beaux Arts Institute of Design, 1923-24 (Box 1, Folder 32-33)
  - Beckwith, Carroll Beckwith, Bertha, 1910-22, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bellows, Emma S., 1925-39 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Benson, Frank W., 1921-44 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Berenson, Bernard, 1924-44 (Box 2, Folder 37-43)
  - Berry, Walter, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Bibliographical File for the Director of American Bibliographies, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Biddle, Edward, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Bitter, Karl, 1910-15 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Blackmore, R.D., 1899 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Blashfield, Edwin H., 1911-53, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 49-50)
  - Bliss, Robert Woods, 1922-54 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Blum, Robert Frederick, 1895, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Blumenschein, Ernst L., 1923-27 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Boardman, Frank C., 1933, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Bodley, J.E.C., 1889-1900 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Britton, James, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Brooks, Van Wyck, 1941-42 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Browne, Archibald, 1922-32 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Brownell, W.C., 1907-34 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Bruce, Edward, 1925-41 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Buchan, John, 1923-54 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Buffalo Fine Arts Academy, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Burlingham, Charles C., 1938-43 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1929-44 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - "C" general, 1902-53, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 65-69)
    Cadmus, Marie
    Cambridge, Walter H.
    Cameron, D.
    Canfield, R.A.
    Carlson, Anna
    Carlson, John F.
    Carmichael, M.
    Carr, Walter Lester
    Carrington, J.B.
    Carter, Morris
    Cartier, Ede
    Caw, James L.
    Century Association
    Chambers, James M.
    Chambrun, Clara Longworth de
    Chapin, James Paul, Mrs.
    Chase, Alice
    Childs, Alfred D.
    Clay, Albert
    Coale, Griffith Baily
    Coleman, Warren
    Colvin, Sidney
    Coolidge, J.
    Cooke, Alan
    Corbett, Harvey W.
    Corrigan, Lillian L.
    Cortissoz, Charles
    Coudert, Frederic R.
    Cragie, Pearl Mary-Teresa
    Cram, Frank
    Cram, R.S.
    Cram, J.B.
    Craven, Thomas
    Crisp, Arthur
    Crocker, F.L.
    Ceroly, Louise
    Crookes, William
    Cross, Emily
    Crowninshield, Frederic
    Cuffy, Willie
    Curran, F.
    Curtis, James F.
    Cutting, Jillian
  - Cadbury, Paul, 1927-29 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Carman, Bliss, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Caro-Delvaille, Henry, 1919-23 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Cary, George, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Castle, Egerton and Alice, 1899-1914, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 74)
    Includes photographs.
  - Chapman, John J., 1916-32 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Chappell, George S., 1929-41 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Clarke, Thomas B., 1914-54 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Clark, Stephen C., 1925 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Cleland, T.M., 1940-53 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Clements, George H., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Coffin, William A., 1912-16 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Colefax, Sibyl, 1928, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Conway, Martin, Sir, 1926-33, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Coolidge, Calvin, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Cortissoz, Royal: Manuscripts and Papers
    - Address at Players Club, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Address to Rembrandt Club (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - American Painting, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Autobiographical Notes and Miscellaneous MS, 1913-43, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Inscriptions, 1912-32, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 89-90)
    - [Adelaide Alsop Robineau], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Biographical Sketch of Edward Palmer York, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - [Cecilia Beaux], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - [Chester Aldrich], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - [Note on William Merritt Chase], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - [Joseph Rodefer De Camp], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - [Edward Guthrie Kennedy], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - [George A. Hearn], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - [Henry Hering], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - [Alden Weir], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - [Notes on Whistler], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 101)
    - Letters to Miss Ambrose, 1942-53 (Box 3, Folder 102)
    - "Notes on My Trip to Cedarville", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 103)
    - Honors and certificates
    - Remarks at Dedication of Statue of Edwin Booth, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 104)
    - Remarks [on Elihu Root], 1929 (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - Remarks on the Memorial Gates, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 106)
    - Summary of Remarks Made at the American Academy in Rome, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 107)
    - [Washington Irving], 1927 (Box 3, Folder 108)
    - [William Rutherford Mead], n.d. (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - Cortissoz, Royal: Outgoing Letters
    - To Buffalo Fine Arts Academy, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 110)
    - To Miss Backus, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 111)
    - To George F. Baker, Jr., 1931 (Box 3, Folder 112)
    - To Adrienne Barry, 1935-44 (Box 3, Folder 113-114)
    - To Erwin S. Barrie, 1933-45 (Box 3, Folder 115-116)
    - To Van Wyck Brooks, 1941-53 (Box 3, Folder 117)
    - To the Carnegie Institute, 1913-53 (Box 3, Folder 118-120)
    - To Morris Carter, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 121)
    - To Albert Clay, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - To T.M. Cleland, 1933-53 (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - To Corcoran Gallery, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - To William Adams Delano, 1941-54 (Box 4, Folder 125-127)
    - To Mr. FInck, 1938-43 (Box 4, Folder 128)
    - To Mrs. Juliana Force, 1927-53 (Box 4, Folder 129)
    - To Mrs. Daniel Chester French, 1933-54 (Box 4, Folder 130)
    - To Lawrence Gilman, 1928-53 (Box 4, Folder 131)
    - To Belle da Costa Greene, 1928-55, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 132-133)
    - To Malvina Hoffman, 1933-53 (Box 4, Folder 134)
    - To Agnes Howell, 1933-53 (Box 4, Folder 135)
    - To August F. Jaccaci, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 136)
    - To William Sergeant Kendall, 1927-53 (Box 4, Folder 137)
    - To Knoedler and Co., 1922-53 (Box 4, Folder 138)
    - To Bancel La Farge, 1911-22 (Box 4, Folder 139)
    - To John La Farge, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 140)
    - To Russell C. Leffingwell, 1943-53 (Box 4, Folder 141)
    - To Mr. Levin, 1937-53 (Box 4, Folder 142)
    - To Samuel Lewisohn, 1929-53 (Box 4, Folder 143)
    - To Mr. Lyman, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 144)
    - To Henry Rutgers Marshall, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 145)
    - To J.P. Morgan, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 146)
    - To Miss Manning, 1937-53 (Box 4, Folder 147)
    - To David Paton, 1911-25, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 148-150)
    - To Mr. and Mrs. C.A. Platt, 1913-34 (Box 4, Folder 151-155)
    - To Marshall Posey, 1938-53 (Box 4, Folder 156)
    - To Frederick Newlin Price, 1924-53 (Box 4, Folder 157)
    - To Whitelaw Reid, 1902-08 (Box 4, Folder 158)
    - To Frederick Wellington Ruckstall, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 159)
    - To Paul J. Sachs, 1925-53 (Box 4, Folder 160)
    - To Henry Schnakenberg, 1941-53 (Box 4, Folder 161)
    - To Miss Toms, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 162)
    - To Dr.and Mrs. Davenport West, 1929-43 (Box 4, Folder 163)
  - Cowles, Anna Roosevelt, 1919-24, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 164)
  - Crawford, F. Marion, 1892-1900 (Box 4, Folder 165)
  - Cret, Paul Philippe, 1929-43 (Box 4, Folder 166)
  - Cross, Wilbur L., 1909-36 (Box 4, Folder 167)
  - Crowninshield, Frank, 1921-41, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 168)
  - Cummings, Homer and Julie, 1943-46 (Box 4, Folder 169)
  - "D" general, 1889-1945, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 170-172)
    Dabney, V.
    Dabo, L.
    Dadge, Mary A.
    Dale, Maud
    "Dalphin", Marcia
    Dana, Paul
    Dana, J.C.
    Darwin, B.
    Dauber, S.
    Davies, Emma L.
    Davies, Virginia M.
    DeGroot, C.H.
    DeMaio, Luigi
    Dennett, Tyler
    Denniston, George F.
    Derby, Lucy
    Deschamps, Charles
    Dewey, John
    Dixey, Henry
    Dodge, William de Leftwich
    Douglas, Malcolm, Dr.
    Downes, W.H.
    Draper, Arthur S.
    Draper, Dorothy
    DuBoise, Guy
    Duncan, F.
    Duncan, Walter Jack
    Dunne, F.P.
    Duplaix, Jeanne, Mrs.
    Dwight, H.G.
  - Damrosch, Walter, 1919-29 (Box 5, Folder 173)
  - Darling, J.N., 1917-40 (Box 5, Folder 174)
  - Davis, Jefferson [to E.C. Stedman], 1888 (Box 5, Folder 175)
  - Davis, John W., 1940-43, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 176)
  - Davis, Charles H., 1925-43 (Box 5, Folder 177)
  - Decamp, Edith, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 178)
  - DeForest, Robert W., 1925-30 (Box 5, Folder 179)
  - Delano, William Adams, 1927-50, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 180)
  - DeManuel, Bernard, 1933, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 181)
  - DeMontreuil, Raymond (Box 5, Folder 182)
  - Dewing, Elizabeth, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 183)
  - Dewing, Maria Oakey, 1921-26, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 184-187)
  - Dewing, T.W., 1895-1919, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 188-189)
  - Douglas, Sholto J., 1912-14, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 190)
  - Drake, A.W., Mr. and Mrs., 1910-41 (Box 5, Folder 191)
  - Drew, John, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 192)
  - Dunn, Gano, 1929-40 (Box 5, Folder 193)
  - Durand-Ruel, 1919-23 (Box 5, Folder 194)
  - Duveen, Joseph, 1914-37 (Box 5, Folder 195-197)
  - "E" general, 1920-31, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 198)
    Earl
    Ehrick, Walter Louis
    Ellingwood, F.L
    Elliott, Jack
    Elliott, M.H.
    Ellsworth, William W.
    Ely, Kerr
    Embury, Aymar
    Evans, Rudulph
  - Edwards, George Wharton, 1911-1924 (Box 5, Folder 199)
  - Erickson, Nancy, 1947-53 (Box 5, Folder 200)
  - "F" general, 1913-53, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 201-204)
    Fackenthal, Frank D.
    Fadiman, Clifton
    Faggi, Alfeo
    Fairman, Charles E.
    Farrell, C.P
    Farrell, Sue M.
    Faulkner, Barry
    Faville, William B.
    Ferguson, J.C.
    Fess, Simeon D.
    Fessender, Elizabeth C.
    Fielding, Mantle
    Finley, David E.
    Finletter, Thomas K., Mrs.
    Finn, Florence Lee
    Fitzpatrick, F.W.
    Flint, Ralph de B.
    Focillon, Marguerite H.
    Forbes, Arch
    Force, Juliana R.
    Ford, James L.
    Ford, Northington C.
    Fortuny, Mariano
    Francis, Robert
    Fraser, Lovat
    Freer, Charles L.
    French, Lillie
    Frew, William
    Frink, L.G.
    Frissell, A.S.
    Frohman, Charles
    Frohman, Daniel
    Frost, Harriett
    Fuller, Lucie Fairchild
    Furay, J.H.
  - Farrand, Beatrix and Max, 1922-30 (Box 5, Folder 205)
  - Farrar, John, 1929, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 206)
  - Ferber, Edna, 1924-40 (Box 5, Folder 207)
  - Finberg, A.J., 1918-31 (Box 5, Folder 208)
  - Finley, John, 1922-25 (Box 5, Folder 209)
  - French, Daniel Chester, 1918-19, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 210)
  - Frick, Helen C., 1921-42 (Box 5, Folder 211)
  - Frost, Arthur Burdett, Sr., 1919, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 212)
  - "G" general, 1895-1945 (Box 5, Folder 213-216)
    Ganners, Lewis
    Garden, N.D.
    Garland, H.
    Garnsey, Elmer E.
    Gazette Des Beaux-Arts
    Genung., Sally
    Gibbons, Douglas
    Gibbons, Thayer
    Gibson, A.
    Gibson, Hamilton
    Gilder, R.W.
    Gilder, Rodman, Mrs.
    Gillette, William
    Glackens, J., Mrs.
    Gladwin, Irving
    Goodhue, Bertram
    Goodrich, Lloyd
    Gould, M.
    Grant, Gordon
    Grant, Robert
    Graves, Charles
    Gray, Henry
    Green, Edward
    Greenbaum, Sophia
    Greenleaf, James
    Greenough, Charlotte
    Greenslet, Ferris
    Grey, William Mrs.
    Griggs, Carolyn
    Griggs, Maitland
    Griswold, T.
    Grossman, Edwin
    Grover, Louise
    Guerry, Prosper
    Guggenheim, Solomon
  - Galantiere, Lewis, 1932-42 (Box 6, Folder 217)
  - Garrison, Wendell P., 1905 (Box 6, Folder 218)
  - Gay, Walter, 1920-28 (Box 6, Folder 219)
  - Gest, J.H., 1926-29 (Box 6, Folder 220)
  - Gibson, Charles Dana, 1918-42 (Box 6, Folder 221)
  - Gilbert, W.S., 1880 (Box 6, Folder 222)
  - Gilbert, Cass, 1924-30 (Box 6, Folder 223)
  - Gilman, Lawrence, 1909-38 (Box 6, Folder 224)
  - Girtin, Thomas and Sabina, 1927-29 (Box 6, Folder 225)
  - Godwin, Harold, 1921-31 (Box 6, Folder 226)
  - Gould, Charles W., 1919-28 (Box 6, Folder 227)
  - Greene, Belle da Costa, 1928-43 (Box 6, Folder 228)
  - "H" general, 1894-1941 (Box 6, Folder 229-232)
    Hail, George, Mrs.
    Hale, Nancy
    Hammond, Perry
    Hampden, Walter
    Hamerton, P.G.
    Harris, Victor
    Harry, George
    Hartmann, Sadakichi
    Harris, William Laurel
    Harrison, J.H.
    Havemeyer, Mary H.
    Haweis, Stephen
    Henderson, H.
    Henderson, W.J.
    Hendrick, Ellwood
    Heney, Charles E.
    Henstees, Louise S.
    Hewett, V.
    Hibben, John
    Higgins, Daniel Paul
    Hind, C. Lewis
    Hind, Henriette Lewis
    Hirsch, Stefan
    Hodge, W.M.
    Hoelzer, C. Fritz
    Holland, Florence
    Holmes, C.
    Holt, Florence
    Holt, Henry
    Holt, Henry, Mrs.
    Hoofer, P.
    Hooker, R.
    Hoover, Earle
    Howe, DeWolfe, M.S.
    Howe, Winifred D.
    Howell, Felicia Waldo
    Hoyt, Everett W.
    Hubbell, George L.
    Hull, Shelley
    Hutchinson, Thomas
    Hymans, Henri
  - Hale, Edward Everett, 1882 (Box 6, Folder 233)
  - Hale, Lilian W., 1925-31 (Box 6, Folder 234)
  - Hammond, Charles A., 1929-30 (Box 6, Folder 235)
  - Hand, Learned, 1919-40 (Box 6, Folder 236)
  - Hare, T.L., 1929-30 (Box 6, Folder 237)
  - Harte, Bret, 1882 (Box 6, Folder 238)
  - Haskell, Ernest and Emma, 1926, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 239)
  - Hassam, Childe, 1928-35 (Box 6, Folder 240)
  - Hastings, Thomas, 1896-29 (Box 6, Folder 241)
  - Havemeyer, Charlotte, 1911-41 (Box 6, Folder 242)
  - Hay, John, 1885-1903 (Box 6, Folder 243)
  - Hermann, Norbert, 1920-29, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 244)
  - Hewlett, Maurice, 1888-1908 (Box 6, Folder 245)
  - Hewlett, J. Monroe, 1916-30 (Box 6, Folder 246)
  - Hills, Laura C., 1908-53 (Box 6, Folder 247)
  - Howells, John Mead, 1931-34 (Box 6, Folder 248)
  - Howells, Mildred, 1932-42 (Box 6, Folder 249)
  - Howells, William Dean, 1899-1912 (Box 6, Folder 250)
  - Hull, Shelley, Mrs., 1941, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 251)
  - Huneker, James, 1902-18 (Box 6, Folder 252)
  - Huntington, Archer, 1907-44 (Box 6, Folder 253)
  - Ivins, William, 1930-32 (Box 6, Folder 254)
  - "J" general, 1920-53 (Box 6, Folder 255)
    James, Walter B.
    Jayne, Horace H.F.
    Jacks, Elizabeth
    Johnson, Howard W.
    Johnson, John G.
    Jones, Bassett
    Jones, Robert Tyre
  - Jaccaci, August, 1905-29 (Box 6, Folder 256)
  - Jackson, Helen, 1882 (Box 6, Folder 257)
  - Jackson, Mrs. "Stonewall", 1882 (Box 6, Folder 258)